Register of the Frances E. Hilger collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Frances E. Hilger collection
1959-1977
79072
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes (8.4 linear feet)
The Frances E. Hilger collection relates to the political activism of Hilger, an opponent of the Vietnam War. A lifelong Quaker, Hilger participated in several peace groups in the New Jersey area. Her collection contains many leaflets, pamphlets, and serial issues published by the anti-war movement, including ephemeral titles. It also contains a number of letters written by Hilger to various politicians, including several United States senators and Congressional representatives.
Hilger, Frances E., collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1917 Born
1960s-1970s Active in movement against the Vietnam War
1977 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Frances E. Hilger collection relates to the political activism of Hilger, an opponent of the Vietnam War. A lifelong Quaker, Hilger participated in several peace groups in the New Jersey area. Her collection contains many leaflets, pamphlets, and serial issues published by the anti-war movement, including ephemeral titles. It also contains a number of letters written by Hilger to various politicians, including several United States senators and Congressional representatives. In addition, there is correspondence relating to other members of Hilger's peace group.
Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World politics--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.
- Biographical File, 1974-1977
  - Clipping, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Obituary, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1967-1977
  - General, 1967-1976
    - A-F, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - G-M, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - N-T, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - U-Z, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Unidentified, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Albert, Carl, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Brink, Paul E., 1974 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Buckley, James L., 1971 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Carroll, Robert, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Case, Clifford P., 1970-1976 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Church, Frank, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Clark, Lindley, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Cooper, John Sherman, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Courier-News, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Cousins, Norman, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Dellums, Ronald V., 1973 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Eisele, Ronald C. (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Ervin, Sam J., Jr., 1973 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Fenwick, Millicent, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Ford, Gerald R., 1976 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Frazier, Howard, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Frelinghuysen, Peter H. B., 1970-1974 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Fulbright, J. W., 1972 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Gallagher, Cornelius E., 1970 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Greer, Germaine, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Gurney, Edward J., 1973 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Haines, Debby, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Hassler, Alfred, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Hébert, F. Edward, 1971 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Helstoski, Henry, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Hughes, Harold E., 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Kennedy, Edward M., 1974 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Kleinhans, Ronnie, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Knight Newspapers, Inc., 1972 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Long, Ngo Vinh, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Mathias, Charles M., 1970-1974 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - McGovern, George, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Meyner, Helen, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Miller, Franklin, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Monroe, Bill, 1971 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Muskie, Edmund S., 1972 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - New York Times (John B. Oakes, James Reston, Kalman Seigel, William Shannon, C. L. Sulzberger), 1969-1974 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Newsweek (Madeleine Edmondson), 1971 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Pell, Clairborne, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - PEACE, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Percy, Charles H., 1974 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Phillips, Richard J., 1969 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Promoting Enduring Peace, Inc., 1970-1973 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Rinaldo, Matthew J., 1976 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Rodino, Peter, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Rogers, William, 1971 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Sandman, Charles W., Jr., 1973 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - SANE (Dorothy Eldridge), 1975 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Saxbe, William B. (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Somerset County Democratic Party, 1973 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Stern, Lee, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Thompson, Frank, Jr., 1973 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Varian, Charles A., 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - WMCA (Fred Gale, Robert E. Grant, R. Peter Straus), 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Williams, Harrison A., Jr., 1970-1976 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Wolfe, Peggy, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Wolff, Lester L., 1973 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Woodward, Peggy, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Minutes of meetings, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Press releases, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1972-1977
  - Notes and fragments, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Announcements and reports, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Writing on William F. Buckley, 1972 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Writing on Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1973 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Poem, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Writing on arms race, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Writing on article by Stanley Ellin, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Writing on public and information, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Writing on Solzhenitsyn, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Writing on American flag and peace, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Writing on anti-communism, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Writing on B-1 bomber, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Writing on human rights, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Writing on politics and Quaker religion, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Writing on the Society of Friends, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Writing on William F. Buckley and Daniel Berrigan, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 21)
- Subject File, 1959-1977
  - Abzug, Bella, 1972 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Afghanistan, 1970 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 4: 1-9)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Angola, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Another Mother for Peace, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Barnet, Richard J., 1974 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Brazil, 1972 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Cambodia, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Chile, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - China, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Church Women United, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 5: 11-12)
  - Committee of Responsibility, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Common Cause, 1973 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Disarmament and arms control, 1965-1977 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Economy, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Eisele, Ronald C., 1970 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Farm workers, 1972 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Fascism, 1971 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1970 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Food policy and hunger, 1975 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 6: 7-9)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
  - Fulbright, J. W., 1976 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Government surveillance and intelligence agencies, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Human rights, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - India-Pakistan War, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Kent State shootings, 1975 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Korea, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Laos, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Latin America, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    Scope and Contents note
    See also separate folders for Brazil and Chile.
  - McGovern, George, 1972 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - McNamara, Robert, 1970 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Media, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Middle East, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Moos, Malcolm, 1975 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - National Action/Research on the Military Industrial Complex (NARMIC), 1972-1974 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Native Americans, 1970 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1972-1974 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Non-violence, 1962-1974 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Nuclear weapons, 1975 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Oil, 1971 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Okinawa, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Peace and Action Committee, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 8: 8-9)
  - Philippines, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Population growth, 1968 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Promoting Enduring Peace, Inc., 1969-1977 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Promoting Enduring Peace, Inc., 1969-1977 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Religion, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - SANE, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
  - Social welfare, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Society of Friends, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Society of Friends, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
  - Taxes, 1974 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - United Nations, 1959-1977 (Box-folder 10: 5-6)
  - United States foreign policy, 1965-1977 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - United States military, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 11: 1-4)
  - Vietnam War, 1967-1977
    - General, 1967-1977 (Box-folder 11: 5-7)
    - General, 1967-1977 (Box-folder 12: 1-7)
    - Aftermath, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Anti-war movement, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
    - Draft resistance, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Human rights, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Prisoners of war, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 13: 5)
    - Refugees, 1972 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - War Resisters League, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Women Strike for Peace, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - World peace, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 13: 10)
- Printed Matter, 1962-1977
  Largely relates to the Vietnam War and anti-war movement.
  - Monographs, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 14: 1-6)
  - Newsletters, 1969-1977
    - General, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 14: 7-8)
    - Cornell Mobe, 1971 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Defense Monitor, 1976 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Disarmament News and Views, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 15: 3)
    - Friends of Children of Vietnam, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - Homefront, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - I. F. Stone's Bi-Weekly, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Newscene, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 15: 7)
    - U.S. and Indochina, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    - US/Indochina Report, 1976 (Box-folder 15: 9)
    - Words by Woods, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 15: 10)
  - Pamphlets, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 16: 1-6)
  - Pamphlets, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 17: 1-6)
  - Pamphlets, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 18: 1-8)
  - Reports, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 18: 9)
  - Serial issues, 1968-1977
    - General, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 19: 1-5)
    - CFC, 1973 (Box-folder 19: 6)
    - Far East Reporter, 1971 (Box-folder 19: 7)
    - Friends Journal (Box-folder 19: 8)
    - Indochina Chronicle, 1971-1977
      - 1971-1973 (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - 1974-1977 (Box-folder 20: 2)
    - Indochina Today, 1973-1974
      - 1973 (Box-folder 20: 3)
      - 1973-1974 (Box-folder 20: 4)
      - 1974 (Box-folder 20: 5-7)
    - Long Island Free Press, 1970 (Box-folder 21: 1)
    - Pacific Research and World Empire Telegram, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 21: 2)
    - Sojourners, 1977 (Box-folder 21: 3)
    - Thòi-Báo Gà, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 21: 4)
    - U.S. Farm News, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 21: 5)
    - Vietnam Report, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 21: 7)